<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of swearing, at all, discussed with several objections answered, the primitive practices therein asserted out of several ancient authors : together with several presidents out of the book of martyrs : the inconveniences that follows the present practice of swearing, which might easily be prevented by a law to punish false witnesse-bearing, and lying as well as other evils : also, a word to all people that are zealous for the commands of Christ, recorded in the Scripture / by a friend of truth and righteousness, John Crook.</title>
            <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13687420</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13687420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101371</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101371)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of swearing, at all, discussed with several objections answered, the primitive practices therein asserted out of several ancient authors : together with several presidents out of the book of martyrs : the inconveniences that follows the present practice of swearing, which might easily be prevented by a law to punish false witnesse-bearing, and lying as well as other evils : also, a word to all people that are zealous for the commands of Christ, recorded in the Scripture / by a friend of truth and righteousness, John Crook.</title>
                  <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101371:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101371:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF SWEARING (AT ALL) DISCUSSED.</p>
            <p>WITH Several Objections anſwered, the Primitive Practiſes therein aſſerted out of ſeveral Ancient Authors; together with ſeveral Preſiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s out of the Book of Martyrs.</p>
            <p>The inconveniences that follows the preſent practice of ſwearing, which might eaſily be prevented, by a Law to puniſh, falſe Witneſſe-bearing, and lying, as well as other evils.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A Word to all People that are zealous for the Commands of CHRIST, recorded in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>By a friend of Truth and Righteouſneſs, <hi>John Crook.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Becauſe of Oaths the Land mourns. And for want of truth and righteouſneſs in the Land, the innocent and uppright are made a prey.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle,</hi> and <hi>Windmill</hi> in <hi>Martins,</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:101371:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101371:2"/>
            <head>The Caſe of ſwearing diſcuſſed.</head>
            <p>MAn was planted a Noble Vine, wholly a right ſeed, but he is turned into the degenerated plant of a ſtrange Vine, more degenerate than the Oxe or the Aſs; he is fallen from the uprightneſs, ſincerity, and ſimplicity, into the invention, ſubtilty, and fleſhly wiſdome, where he lies grovelling upon the earth, thinking by the multitude of his inventions, to recover himſelf, and to come to life again; but he is fenced out with a flaming Sword, ſo that to life he cannot come, but through death, which he ſeeks to avoid, by following the counſel of the Evil-One, who ſayes (in this) as he did formerly to the woman, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dye;</hi> though God had ſaid, (as it is written) <hi>Of the tree of knowledge of good and evil, thou ſhalt not eat of it, for in the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> And alſo that which the Apoſtle feared might come upon ſome of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> is come upon all the world, <hi>viz.</hi> The Serpent that beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> hath beguiled men and women in this age, through his ſubtilty, by corrupting their mindes from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt; and as the Deceiver then denyed what God had ſpoken, and not onely ſo, but alſo put his own meaning and expoſition upon Gods Command, that ſo he might accompliſh his end; for ſaid the Perverter then, <hi>God doth know that in the day thou eateſt thereof, your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods, knowing good and evil.</hi> And hath not the ſame Serpent beguiled the people of this age, from the naked ſimplicity, to hearken to the diſguized ſubtilty and fleſhly wiſdome, not onely to deny that Chriſt hath given out an abſolute Command, that his followers ſhould not ſwear at all, (by any Oath) but alſo as he did then, ſo he hath done ſince, and doth do now in this age, put his expoſition and meaning to Chriſts commands, in ſaying in ſome men, that it is not all ſwearing that is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101371:3"/>but ſwearing in mens ordinary communication: This expoſition, the ſubtilty in ſome men puts upon Chriſts Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, whereupon the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conclude, that notwithſtanding Chriſts command not to ſwear at all, yet when any man is called before a Magiſtrate, if the Magiſtrate require it, he ought to ſwear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which it is ſaid, Chriſts own words at the 33 Verſe of the fifth of <hi>Matthew,</hi> anſwers this objection, in theſe words: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain it hath been ſaid in old time, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform to the Lord thy Oaths; but I ſay unto you, Swear not at all, &amp;c.</hi> (Mark) <hi>Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, &amp;c.</hi> The Law in old time did not allow of ſwearing in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary communication, and dealing, for that was taking Gods Name in vain, <hi>Exodus</hi> 20.7. which was forbidden from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nning, but in that caſe wherein they were allowed to ſwear, they were not to forſwear themſelves: But Chriſt Jeſus the Son, by whom the Father ſpeaks in theſe laſt times, <hi>(who is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs) to all that believe in him,</hi> who is the truth and ſubſtance of all, ſayes, <hi>Swea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not at all.</hi> (Mark) the truth ſayes, <hi>ſwear not at all, for whatever is more then yea, and nay, comes of evil.</hi> Now if Chriſt, the Truth, had ſpoken no more in theſe words, <hi>Swear not at all, &amp;c.</hi> then to forbid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſwearing (as they call it) or not ſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g in mens or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary communication, what doth he forbid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore then was forbidden in <hi>old time?</hi> ſeeing, as before is proved, that all prophane ſwearing, which is a taking of Gods Name in vain, or ſwearing in ordinary communication, or dealing, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden from the beginning. And again, how doth this hold parallel with the reſt of Chriſts ſayings and compariſons, <hi>viz.</hi> What <hi>was ſaid in the old time by the Law,</hi> and is now ſaid by himſelf, who is the ſum <hi>and end of the Law for righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> and whether they who thus reaſon, do not by their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions make Chriſts Command of none effect? And do not all thoſe that plead that the Saints ought and may ſwear, when they are called to it by a Magiſtrate, not onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> break Chriſts Commands themſelves, but teaches others ſo to do? whoſe portion may be read in <hi>Matthew</hi> 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>19. and by their thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning in their dark mindes, make Chriſt to ſpeak nothing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101371:3"/>further, nor fuller, then was ſpoken in old time, though <hi>in old time it was ſaid, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thy Oaths, &amp;c.</hi> But ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I ſay unto you, ſwear not at all:</hi> Now let all judge, who are not blinded, through gain or tradition, whether thoſe that ſay the Saints ought to ſwear (when called to it as aforeſaid) do not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make void theſe words, viz. <hi>Whatſoever is more then theſe commeth of evil;</hi> and ſo they being in the evil, are blinded, and hate the light that would let them ſee, and ſpeak evil of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it would reprove them, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in darkneſs, they know not whither they go; but as ſaith the Prophet, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſay,</hi> 5 20. <hi>call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arkneſs light, and light darkneſs, and good evil, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d evil good.</hi> And it is further manifeſt to all that have an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to ſee, that <hi>Chriſt, the ſubſtance and the truth,</hi> in ended as he ſpake, when he ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> which was to forbid all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anner of ſwearing, without exception; becauſe when Chriſt inten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed an exception at the 32 Verſe, he ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſed it in theſe words: <hi>But I ſay unto you, Whoſoever ſhall put awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife, ſaving for the cauſe of Adultery.</hi> (Mark) <hi>ſaving for the cauſe of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery;</hi> Where Chriſt plainly expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth the exception: But for proud men to make exceptions, where Chriſt hath made none, is to ſet Self on the Throne. And again, at the 28 Verſe the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is expreſſed, viz. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall look upon a woman, and luſt after her.</hi> Mark) <hi>to luſt after her,</hi> and is not leſt to vain man to put his meaning to it.</p>
            <p>It is further objected by ſome, that by thoſe <hi>of old time</hi> is meant the Expoſitors of the Law, who ſaid, If men ſwear truth, that was no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> evil, but onely they were not to ſwear to that which was falſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which it is anſwered, that this being an invention of the Objector, and no where ſo ſaid in the Scripture of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, it needs no other anſwer then a denyal, but the word in the Greek reads it thus, <hi>It was ſaid to them of old time,</hi> thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying thoſe to whom and by whom God ſpake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ant quis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongly ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected, That the Apoſtle in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> allows of ſwearing before a Magiſtrate; as in <hi>Hebrews</hi> 6.16. in theſe words, <hi>For men verily ſwears by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101371:4"/>greater, and an Oath for confirmation, is to them an end of all ſtrife,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To which is replyed, there the Apoſtle by a ſimilitude makes it out to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> how that God ſware by himſelf, becauſe he could not ſwear by a greater, to confirm the Promiſe, <hi>That by two immutable things, by which it was not poſſible for God to lye, that they might have ſtrong conſolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope ſet before them; and God being more abundantly willing to ſhew to the Heirs of the promiſe the immutability of his Counſel, confirmed it by an Oath,</hi> which thing was uſed among men that lived in ſtrife, to put an end to ſtrife, they uſed an Oath, and they ſware by the greater, an Oath for confirmation was to them an end of all ſtrife, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God could not ſwear by a greater, he ſware by himſelf, and by the Oath of God is the promiſe confirmed to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſeed, that they might have ſtrong conſolation, no more to ſuffer ſtrife, and fears, and doubts, to enter upon them; but that they all might witneſs in themſelves, an end put to all ſtrife and contention, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as truly and really in the inward man, by Chriſt Jeſus, Gods Oath, and Covenant, as an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Oath uſed among men (that live in ſtrife) was to them <hi>for confirmation the end of all ſtrife:</hi> And in this caſe under the Law was an Oath required, <hi>Exodus</hi> 22.10. <hi>If a man deliver unto his neighbour an Oxe, or an Aſſe, or a ſheep, or any beaſt to keep, and it die, or be hurt, or driven away, no man ſeeing it, then ſhall an Oath of the Lord be between them both, that he hath not put his hand to his neighbours goods, and the Owner of it ſhall accept thereof, and he ſhall not make it good.</hi> (Mark) the Owner of the goods was to accept thereof, <hi>and he ſhall not make it good:</hi> ſo an Oath for confirmation was an end to the controverſie, and in this <hi>old time</hi> under the Law, they were not to forſwear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but Chriſt ſayes, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> who is <hi>the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Now the Apoſtle never intended (by that which was uſed <hi>in old time,</hi> and among men that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in ſtrife, all which he brings in as a compariſon and a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude to confirm the promiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and not to incourage men to break Chriſts Commands, who ſayes, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> nor to give any ſort of men incouragement to walk contrary
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101371:4"/>to the Apoſtles Doctrine, who ſaid, <hi>Above all things my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſwear not, &amp;c.</hi> Neither that they ſhould take incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his compariſon <hi>to live in ſtrife,</hi> becauſe men that uſed ſwearing <hi>at all,</hi> did ſo; neither did the Apoſtle any more intend to lay a foundation for ſwearing, or for men to impoſe Oaths upon others, by his ſimilitude of what was uſed among ſtrifeful men, then he intended that the Miniſters of Chriſt ſhould bring a Heathen Poet to prove their Doctrine, becauſe he ſayes, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. <hi>As certain alſo of your own Poets have ſaid, &amp;c.</hi> And may it not be as juſtly concluded that Parents ſhould take incouragement to correct their children after their own pleaſure, becauſe he ſayes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.10. <hi>We have had Fathers of our fleſh, who for a few dayes chaſtiſed us after their own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, &amp;c.</hi> And as honeſtly as it may or ought to be concluded, that the Apoſtle intended that men ſhould either ſwear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>at all,</hi> or compel others ſo to do. from theſe words, <hi>viz. For verily menſwears by the greater, and an Oath for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to them an end of all ſtrife.</hi> And further, is there any more ground given by the Apoſtle fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Saints to ſwear <hi>at all,</hi> by any Oath from the words before-mentioned, then there is ground from Chriſts words to the Saints <hi>to exerciſe Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hip one over another,</hi> becauſe he ſayes, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.42. <hi>the Gentiles do ſo:</hi> Beſides, did not thoſe that uſed ſwearing, uſe it onely in thoſe caſes where an Oath would <hi>put an end to all ſtrifes?</hi> But is not Oaths impoſed at this day where no ſtrife is? Nay, are they not impoſed for the beginning of ſtrife? Let the righteous judge how far thoſe that would be accouned Saints, are fallen, that they are ſhort in their practiſes of thoſe men that lived in ſtrife in ages paſt.</p>
            <p>Again, to impoſe Oaths upon others from the Apoſtles words, is to make the Apoſtle a Tranſgreſſor; for he ſayes, <hi>Galathians</hi> 2.18. <hi>If I build again the things that I deſtroyed, am I not a Tranſgreſſor?</hi> Now he condemned ſome among the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> for walking as men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>For ye are yet carnal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is envying among you, diviſion and ſtrife; are you not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and walk as men?</hi> (Mark) there was <hi>ſtrife</hi> and <hi>diviſion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and from thence he proves them carnal, and therefore they walk <hi>as men,</hi> which the Apoſtle condemns;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101371:5"/>whereas they ſhould walk as became Saints, who are redemed from among men, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.14. out of <hi>envy, ſtrife, and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and are called unto <hi>love, righteouſneſs, and peace,</hi> which all who walk as becomes Saints witneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> That an oath cannot be bad, becauſe even God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did often uſe ſwearing in Scripture <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it may become God alone to ſwear, becauſe he alone is true, and cannot lye, but all men a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lyars, as ſayes the Apoſtle; <hi>And the Lord hath ſworn, and will not repent, Pſa.</hi> 110.4. Let him then ſwear that cannot repent of his Oath, and he is not to be imitated in ſwearing by that man, who cannot imitate him in fulfilling.</p>
            <p>It is again objec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> by ſome, that all proceedings at Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon ſwearing therefore they conclude that all men muſt ſwear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the foundation of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> and the preſent practiſe and proceedings thereupon, do not agree; as may appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e inſtances following, <hi>viz.</hi> One main and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal foundation of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> is the Law of God; ſo ſayes the Law-book, Docter and Student, <hi>Chapter</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 4. in theſe words, <hi>There is a Law written in the heart of man, which is man created in the Image of God; and this Law is alwayes good and righteous, ſtirring up the man to do the goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and abhor the evil; and therefore againſt this Law</hi> (ſayes the book) <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, Statute, Cuſtome, may not prevail; and if any be brought in againſt it, they be void, and againſt Juſtice.</hi> Now conſider, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your Law, how few proceedings are according to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and inſtead of being made void, as being againſt Juſtice, they are incouraged, and hath been.</p>
            <p>Again, it is the Law of <hi>England,</hi> 9. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.29. <hi>That Right and juſtice ſhould neither be ſold, deferred, nor denie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to any man, &amp;c.</hi> But let thoſe that have to do at Courts, ſpeak and bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whether both denying and delaying, both of Law and Right, be not that which they meet withall, and for ſelling and buying of it, let the great and exceſſive Fees which ſome Lawyers take for pleading ſpeak, who are in repute; and as the people ſay, if you can but retain ſuch a man, you need not fear your Cauſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101371:5"/>
            <p>Again, it is the Law of <hi>England, that none ſhould be put into Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice upon ſuit, or for favour or affection, but upon deſert;</hi> 12 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2.2. 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.16. The firſt part of <hi>Cooks Inſtitutes, page</hi> 2.34. A Law (ſayes <hi>Cook) worthy to be written in letters of Gold.</hi> But how contrary to theſe Statutes the preſent practiſes are, let the righteous judge.</p>
            <p>Further, both by the Common-law, and Statute law, the Judges were not to hear the Plantiffs Cauſe, if he <hi>firſt put not in ſecurity to anſwer his Adverſaries damages, if he complained of him wrongfully, Mirror. page</hi> 64. 37 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 18. 38 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 9. And he that chargeth a man with any accuſation, ought to put in Security to make good his accuſation; and the Law hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a puniſhment for him, that makes not his accuſation good; But how contrary the preſent practiſes and proceedings of Courts are at this day, let the Cauſes that comes into them ſpeak: Do not they iſſue out their Writs, grounded upon divers plain and notorious lyes? As that they have ſent to the Sheriff of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> (which they have not done) and that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, that the Party is not within his Liberty, (which he hath not done) but lies lurking in another County, (which is moſt commonly falſe, the man going up and down as at other times) and the Sheriff of <hi>Middleſex</hi> knowing nothing of it. Again, They ſay, they have taken Pledges to proſecute, <hi>viz; John Doe,</hi> and <hi>Richard Roe,</hi> which is alſo a Deceipt, and a Lye, thoſe being common feigned names put into all Writs, and theſe Writs made up of ſo many lyes, (being framed by any Clerk, and given forth in the chief Magiſtrates name) is borne witneſs to be the Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> is the ground and foundation of all proceedings at Law; whereby the known Law of <hi>England,</hi> in Caſes of Debt, men ought to be firſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appear to anſwer the Plantiff before they be arreſted; but how contrary the preſent proceedings are, let all ſober men judge.</p>
            <p>Again, the Law ſaves, <hi>Mirror. page</hi> 2. 49. <hi>It is an abuſe of the Common-Law, to appear or anſwer by an Attorney:</hi> But the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent practiſe is quite contrary; for they have, and do deny, to accept of a mans Appearance in perſon, although the words of their own Writs are ſo, In theſe words, <hi>So that we may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101371:6"/>have his body before us at our Court at Weſtminſter, ſuch a day, &amp;c.</hi> And it is further evidenced, that the Appearing by an <hi>Attorney</hi> was firſt in favour, and in eaſe of the Subject, that ſo they might depute one for their eaſe; as in the book <hi>De Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati Faciendo;</hi> but now ſo is Juſtice and Judgement turned backward, that that which was for the eaſe of the people, is now made uſe of, to maintain a trade of deceipt. It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Cooks Reports,</hi> in <hi>Richard Go frey's</hi> Caſe, that <hi>Exceſſus in re qualibet, jure reprobatur communi; as exceſſive diſtreſſes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive aids, exceſſive ame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciaments, are againſt the Common-Law.</hi> And how contrary the preſent practiſes is, let the proceedings againſt the innocent people (called <hi>Quakers</hi>) bear witneſs in d vers Counties in <hi>England,</hi> who have been fined more then they have been worth, ſome it may be for not ſwearing, and others for not reſpecting of mens perſons; but Preſidents e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough may be ſeen of their cruel Oppreſſions in this kinde, in a book in Print, called, <hi>The Record of the ſufferings for Tythes,</hi> and in moſt Priſons in <hi>England,</hi> examples of exceſſive cruelty may be found exerciſed upon poor innocent people, becauſe they cannot ſubmit to pay theſe exceſſive Fines impoſed on them, contrary to any known Law, and the practiſes of Ages paſt; but ſuch men flye to Cuſtome, when no known Law can be found, and abuſe the word <hi>Cuſtome</hi> as many Juſtices do, and have done the word <hi>Diſcretion;</hi> neither of them warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the practiſes of proud ſelf-willed men, there being <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> that are evill, which ought to be aboliſhed, as ſayes the Law; and <hi>Cook in his Reports in Gatewards Cauſe,</hi> ſayes, <hi>Cuſtome</hi> ought to be reaſonable, <hi>Et excerta Cauſa rationab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitata;</hi> as <hi>Littleton</hi> ſayes: and if every Cuſtome ſhould be a Law, becauſe Judges calls them ſo, ſurely it may be ſaid, that King and Biſhops would have been ſtill ſtanding in <hi>England;</hi> and the word <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> is as much abuſed by corrupt men, they making it a Cloak to cover their deceitful Actings, when they have no Law to warrant their practiſes: But <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> as <hi>Cook</hi> ſayes, <hi>is a knowledge or underſtanding to diſcern betwixt truth and falſhood, and between right and wrong, between ſhadowes and ſubſtance, and between equity, and colourable gloſſes and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and not to do according to our wills, and private affections;</hi> For,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101371:6"/>ſayes he, <hi>Talis diſcretio, diſceſſionem confundit, and hath been adjudged in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of Commiſſion of Suers, Diſcretion is to be bounded with Reaſon, Law, and Juſtice;</hi> and ſo the word <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> is abuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> urged by corrupt men, in oppoſition to the expreſs Command of Chriſt, Who ſayes, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe Exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les the honeſt-hearted may ſee, how contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> practiſes of the Law is to the foundation of the Law; and to that which is good, being uſed lawfully, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a dead thing, <hi>execution being the Life of the Law;</hi> and hereby the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ghteous, that it is not made for, is moſt hurt by it, and the <hi>Flatterer</hi> and <hi>Evil-doer</hi> incouraged; therefore their reaſoning is not good, who ſay all men ought to ſwear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of long time they have uſed to do ſo, and continue ſtill to do ſo; therefore the queſtion is not, what men do practiſe, but what men ought to practiſe, according to a true Rule, and Line. For we read not (that I remember) among all <hi>Iſraels</hi> Laws, that any of their Officers were made by an Oath, <hi>as Judges, Rulers, Kings, or Prieſts, or Prophets,</hi> or required to ſwear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they took the work or Office upon them: But we read, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 19.15. <hi>At the mouth of two, or at the mouth of three Witneſſes, ſhall the matter be eſtabliſhed.</hi> (Mark) <hi>the matter was to be eſtabliſhed without ſwearing:</hi> For if they ſhould have been firſt ſworn, it would have been ſo written, it being a Command to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and in the caſe of Life and Death, <hi>At the mouth of two or three Witneſſes, ſhall he that is worthy of Death be put to Death; but at the mouth of one Witneſs he ſhall not be put to Death.</hi> In this caſe of Life and Death, no Oath was uſed that we read of, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 17.6. And if any falſe Witn ſs did ariſe, he, and the party he witneſſed againſt, was to ſtand befo e the Lord, and before the Prieſt, and Judges which ſhould be in thoſe dayes, and the Judges were to make diligent inquiſition, <hi>And if the Witneſs be a falſe Witneſs, and have teſtified falſly againſt his Brother, then ſhall ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o unto him, as he had thought to have done unto his Brother, ſo ſhall you put away the evil from among you, Deut.</hi> 1916, 17, 18. But no ſwearing is mentioned; and if any matter did ariſe too hard for them in judgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween blood and blood, between plea and plea, and ſtroak and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101371:7"/>ſtroak, being matters of controverſie within their gate, they were not to ſwear men to finde it out, neither were they to act pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptiouſly their own paſſion and wills, and then cover it, with ſaying they were Judges of the Law, and they judged it ſo, and many things being left to diſcretion; and therefore ſayes wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men, in the ſtoutneſs of thei hearts, If we do what we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer, take your courſe againſt us: And thus preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly do they act their own wills upon the innocent, but <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not to do ſo; but in caſes too hard for them in judgement, they were to ariſe and go up to the place, which the Lo d God ſhould chooſe, and they were to come to the Prieſt and Levite, and unto the Judges which ſhould be in thoſe dayes, and enquire, and they were to ſhew the Sentence of Judgement, and they were to do according to the Sentence which they of the place, which the Lord ſhould chooſe, ſhould ſhew therein; <hi>And thou ſhalt obſerve to do according to all that they ſhall inform thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And the man that will do preſumptiouſly, and will not hearken to the Prieſts that ſtands up there, to miniſter before the Lord thy God or unto the Judges, even that man ſhall die, and thou ſhalt put away the evil from</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. This was Gods Law to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that the <hi>Preſumptious</hi> that would not wait upon the Lord to receive a Law where there was none, <hi>ſhould be put to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it an offence of old to act <hi>preſumptiouſly?</hi> And is it not now a crime worthy to be taken notice of by the chief in power in theſe dayes? Or are there none that have done preſumptiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? in caſting innocent people into priſon, when they have done no offence, nor broken no known Law, except it is become an offence to wait upon the Lord, and to pray unto him, for which cauſe, and none other, the innocent have been caſt into priſon by the preſumptious and ſelf-willed men, who when they had no Law, have acted in their wills, contrary to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w; let ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that by Gods Law, they that would not wait upon the Lord for a Law, but would act <hi>preſumptiouſly</hi> without a Law, were to be put to death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> That by not ſwearing at all, we are to underſtand by any creature, and not by God the Creator, for they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſwear by God, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſwear by the Lord;</hi> as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101371:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That according to Chriſts own words, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> without any exception, as before hath been proved, and is expounded in the large Bible in <hi>Quarto,</hi> in the Margent, on <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.37. in theſe words, <hi>VVhatſoever you vouch, vouch it barely; and whatſoever you deny, deny it barely, without any more words; for whatſoever is more then theſe, comes of the Devil:</hi> And alſo in the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e book it is ſaid, on <hi>James</hi> 5.12. <hi>That what you have to ſay, or affirm, ſpeak or affirm it ſimply, and without any Oath, and that that you will deny, deny ſimply and flatly.</hi> And again, this Objection is more fully anſwered in <hi>Matthew</hi> 23.21, 22. <hi>VVhoſoever ſwears by the Temple, ſwears by it, and by him that dwells therein; and whoſoever ſwears by heaven, ſwea s by the Throne of God, and him that ſits thereon:</hi> So that he that ſwears by the creature, ſhall not be exempted by the Creator from prophaning his name; for now it is ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, it is objected by the former Objectors, (who ſayes all proceedings at Law depends upon ſwearing) that if we ſhould take every mans word, when they are called to give their teſtimony in all caſes, it might be of dangerous conſequence both to mens lives, liberties, and eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which it is anſwered, That if the ſame Law, or a ſtricter, were made againſt lying, and bearing falſe witneſs, in all caſes, as againſt mens ſwearing, falſe ſwearing, or for-ſwearing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that Law t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul and conſtantly executed, without reſpect of perſons, it would then be of no more danger to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a mans yea or nay to the queſtions that are asked him by the Magiſtrate, whatever they be, then if they had kiſſed the book, or uſed any other poſture with the hand, or ſpoken never ſo many words (his affirming or denying to the caſe in queſtion, being his teſtimony) I ſay the truth of theſe mens teſtimonies may as eaſily, plainly, and fully be diſcerned, and puniſhed, according to the Law in that caſe provided, if it be falſe as if the had uſed never ſo many words, or poſtures, as aforeſaid; a d therefore mens lives, liberties, and eſtates, may every way be as well ſecured by a Law provided to puniſh lying and bea ing falſe witneſs, as by any Law that is made, or can be made, to puniſh ſwearing, or falſe-ſwearing, ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101371:8"/>Again, as to the preſent ſtate of things, becauſe there is no Law in being, as ſome ſay, to puniſh lying, therefore we muſt ſwear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Law is there to force men to ſwear, or to puniſh thoſe that ſwear falſly, or againſt their knowledge, to their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to Bills in <hi>Chancery</hi> and <hi>Chequor?</hi> And is it not common and ordinary for men ſo to do? If there be a Law, why is it not put in execution? or doth Cuſtome make ſwearing falſly (and againſt a mans knowledge) no offence; and a mans ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truly, without ſwearing, an offence puniſhable with impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment? Who hath given this authority to Cuſtome? Let E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity anſwer: But of this more may be ſpoken afterward in its place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> That an Oath is a ſolemn thing, and that when people are called before a Magiſtrate to ſwear, there is an awe upon them; and therefore thoſe that are wicked, and Lyars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are afraid to forſwear themſelves, when called before a Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>This Objection is for what anſwered in the preceding Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: But further it is anſwered, That the fear upon People when they come to ſwear, is either the fear of God, which is good, or ſome other fear which is evill, as the fear of man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and his puniſhment; this laſt fear is not to be feared by thoſe that fear the Lord; <hi>Fear ye not their fear, but fear him that can deſtroy both ſoul a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y;</hi> and this fear is pure, and keeps the heart clean, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od is ſeen, and deceit and guile is kept out, a ditruth is ſpoken in all caſes; and he that abides in the fear of the Lord, ſtands in awe, and ſins nor, and is kept not only from wearing, but lying alſo: but he that onely fears man, and his puniſhment, when he comes to know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that there is as great or greater puniſhment to be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him for his lying, as for his falſe ſwearing, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing himſelf, or bearing falſe witneſs; then he alſo will ſtand in as much fear of a Lye, as of an Oath; (or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t which is called ſo) beſides, it is commonly ſeen by experience, that thoſe who care not what they ſpeak, matters not much what they ſwear, if ſo be they can but keep from the puniſhment of the Law; but it is not ſo with the Righteous, for the fear of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101371:8"/>the Lord makes them ſober and ſolid, and their words to be few and ſavoury, ſeaſoned with truth; but thoſe that fear man, and his diſpleaſure and puniſhment only, when they know the ſame Law to be in force again lying, as againſt ſwearing, or ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſly, they will then be as ſolemn, and as afraid to lye, as now to forſwear themſelves.</p>
            <p>It is objected by others, who ſay the Scripture is their rule, that the holy men in old time did ſwear, as we may read under the Law, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſware, and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon:</hi> to all which it is ſaid, Chriſt is the end of the Law; and he who is the Oath of God, by whom God ſpeaks in theſe laſt dayes, ſayes, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and he that is greater then <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe day <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw; but he himſelf is now come, and ſayes, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and he who is <hi>Davids</hi> Lord ſayes, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> who is the end of the Prophets, the everlaſting High-Prieſt and Covenant of God, the ſumme and ſubſtance of all the things, the Law was but a ſhadow of; Who is the Truth, the Life, and the Way to the Father, and teaches all his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to ſpeak truth to their neighbour, and to walk in the truth, (which makes free from ſwearing <hi>at all</hi>) notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the traditions of their Fathers in the fleſh, or the practiſes of ſtrifeful men; for by Chriſt the Truth, they are taught to ſpeak truth, and not to fear them that can but kill the body, but to fear him that can caſt both ſoul and body into hell, which fear he hath placed in their hearts, that they might not depart from him, but abide in his Doctrine, which ſayes, <hi>Swear not all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is further objected by ſome, that the Angel ſware in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> and that <hi>Paul</hi> ſware, as may be read in his Epiſtles, in ſaying, <hi>I proteſt before God;</hi> and in often ſaying, <hi>I call the Lord God to Witneſs,</hi> which is ſaid to be an Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt that the Angel ſware, it is ſaid, <hi>Let all the Angels worſhip him,</hi> Who hath ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And to that that <hi>Paul</hi> proteſted before God, it is the intruſion of the Tranſlator, it being neither in the Greek Copies, nor Latine, nor ſome Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Copies.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, That he calls God to Witneſs, that is no Oath, but onely an earneſt atteſtation, an Oath being that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101371:9"/>by ſomething is ſworn by, (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to ſwear by the Name of the Lord) and calling God to witneſs, or ſaying, <hi>God is my Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> is no more then to ſay, I ſpeak in Gods preſence, or before him who knowes the hearts and thoughts of all men, and is no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Oath (as it is called, or commonly uſed in oppoſition to a plain and earneſt expreſſion of a mans mind.)</p>
            <p>Again, it is objected, that not to ſwear at all is only Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal counſel, and not an abſolute prohibition of all ſwearing in all caſes, though it be ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> and yet in ſome caſes it is lawfull to kill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That forbidding to ſwear at all, is no where in Scripture called Evangelical Counſel; but ſuch an Abſolute and Poſitive Command, and backed with the Apoſtles Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, that I know not any Command fuller in the Scripture of truth: And whereas it is ſaid, That to kill, is a prohibition, and yet in ſome caſes allowable yet it is no where ſo ſaid of ſwearing, (in the New Teſtament, or) ſince the time of its prohibition, that it is lawful in any caſe to ſwear; neither was it practiſed in the firſt ages of the true Church, as may a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pear hereafter in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, under the head of Preſidents of them who denyed ſwearing; and though it be lawful in ſome caſes to kill, (though it be ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill</hi>) yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is no where ſaid, it is lawful to ſwear in any caſe, as aforeſaid, but on the contrary, Wo be unto them that brings a Chriſtian to ſuch a neceſſity, that he muſt ſwear, as woe attends them that neceſſitates a Chriſtian to kill.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101371:9"/>
            <head>Now follows ſeveral Preſidents, or Examples, both out of Holy W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it, and Antient Authors of the beſt repute among them that are called learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</head>
            <p>FIrſt, in the Scripture of truth in the Old Teſtament, where in the ſeveral caſes wherein ſwearing was uſed, is recorded; as <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.11. <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Deuter.</hi> 6.13. and 10.20. <hi>Jeremy</hi> 12.16. <hi>Amos</hi> 8.14. <hi>Zepha.</hi> 1.5. (theſe being the particular caſes and occaſions wherein ſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing is mentioned) where the Reader may obſerve at his leaſure the caſes in which ſwearing is uſed, and the ground, and cauſe, and end of it; but neither was the <hi>Judges, nor Rulers, nor Prophets, nor Prieſts, nor Kings, nor any other Officer</hi> that we read of, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted or made by an oath, as neceſſary to let him into his work, or office, or place, or imployment, or that without which he could not ſo officiate, or be imployed; but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, an oath was not ſo much as tendered to them, or required at their hands; neither in the greateſt accidents or caſes that fell out in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was it to be determined by thoſe which were ſworn, or took an oath, except before excepted in the caſe of goods committed to his Neighbour to keep, &amp;c. <hi>Exodus</hi> 22.11. and the woman in caſe of Adultery, <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.21. who was to purge her ſelf by an oath, and ſo was determined by a ſignal and eminent judgment upon her: but in all other caſes, as in particular, between ſtroak and ſtroak, and plea and plea; and in caſes of greateſt moment, as of life and death, they were all to be determined without an oath, and the falſe witneſs on either ſide was to be puniſhed, according to the appointment of the Law: And in the New Teſtament, by Chriſt (the great Prophet and High-Prieſt of our profeſſion) it is ſo fully and abſolutely forbidden, and bound up with this word, <hi>Not at all,</hi> that nothing is plainer either in the Old or New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and this continued in, and preached by his Apoſtles
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101371:10"/>particularly by <hi>James,</hi> who gives this the preheminence, in a peculiar manner, above all other things, that thoſe whom he wrote to ſhould be carefull to keep and obſerve, ſaying, <hi>Above all things my Brethren ſwear not; neither by Heaven nor Earth, nor any other oath.</hi> (which is an abſolute negative excluſion of all ſwearing in all caſes.) And <hi>Euſebius,</hi> an Antient Writer of no mean eſteem among the learned, writes in his ſixth book, <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 4 <hi>page</hi> 98. about the year 200. that <hi>Baſilides,</hi> a Souldier, unto wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m the Virgin <hi>Potamioena</hi> was committed, as one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dome: <hi>But not long after, the ſame</hi> Baſilides <hi>being required by his fellow-ſouldiers to ſwear upon ſome occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (that fell out) <hi>affirmed plainly, it was not lawful for him to ſwear, for he ſaid he was a Chriſtian, and that he would in very deed proteſt the ſame;</hi> who afterward was beheaded as a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr:</hi> And of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> of whom the firſt Book of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> makes much mention, and are ſaid by ſome immediately to ſucceed the Apoſtles, and were diſperſed into moſt parts of the world, and to be the moſt antient and true <hi>Proteſtants,,</hi> (as may be ſeen by what <hi>Fox</hi> records of them in the Book of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi>) and this they maintained among other things, that all manner of ſwearing was unlawfull; as may appear by <hi>Parſons, Sanders, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>occius,</hi> and others; and by Biſhop <hi>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her</hi> (a late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a man reputed for learning) who hath by way of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> in this caſe of ſwearing, ſeemed to juſtifie them therein; as in his book <hi>De Succeſ. Cap.</hi> 6. And the ſaid <hi>Uſher</hi> further ſayes in his eighth Chap. (quoting ſome antient Authors) <hi>that the</hi> Waldenſes, <hi>as well as Anabaptiſts of late, did profeſſe it to be no way lawfull for a Chriſtian to ſwear, upon any occaſion;</hi> And <hi>Theophil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te</hi> upon <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.37. <hi>Sayes, that though in the time of the Old Law it was not ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l to ſwear; but ſince the coming of Chriſt it is evil, as is Circumciſion, and in ſum, whatever is judaical, for it may become a Child to ſuck, but not a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further in the Book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> 1 Voll. <hi>page</hi> 701. it is charged againſt <hi>William Thorp,</hi> in his Sermon that he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> that it is not lawfull to ſwear in any caſe: To which he anſwered, he denied to ſwear by a book, as being made up of creatures and quoats; <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in theſe words,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101371:10"/>
               <hi>who blamed them greatly, who brought forth books to ſwear, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they think a man to ſwear true or falſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Arch-biſhop and his Clarks ſcorned this ſaying of <hi>Thorp,</hi> and the Biſhop manaced him with great puniſhment, except he left this opinion of ſwearing; to which <hi>Thorp</hi> anſwered, it was not his Opinion, but the opinion of Chriſt, and of Saint <hi>James,</hi> and of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and of other divers Saints and Doctors: The Arch-biſhop cauſed to be read this Homily of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> which the Clark did accordingly, until he came to a Clauſe where <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayes, <hi>That it is ſin to ſwear well,</hi> &amp;c. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in <hi>Fox,</hi> Voll. 1. pa. 527. in the Ploughmans prayer, in theſe words, <hi>Thou gaveſt us a Commandment in truth, in bidding us ſay yea, yea, nay, nay, and ſwear for nothing: Thou gaveſt us alſo a Commandment of meekneſs, and another of poorneſs; but Lord he that cleepeth himſelf thy Vickar on earth, hath both bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken theſe Commandments, for he makes a Law to compel men to ſwear, and by his Law he teacheth, that a man to ſave his life, may forſwear and lye; and ſo Lord, through comfort of him, and his Law, the people ne dreadeth not to ſwear, and to liven ought time to forſwear them; Lord here is little truth, &amp;c.</hi> Again, <hi>William Swinderby,</hi> an Article charged againſt him, <hi>that no man owns to ſwear for any thing, but ſimply without an Oath, to affirm or deny, and if he ſwears, he ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe that are converſant in our Law, (what was the practice in antient time) where they teſtifie that Oaths an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently were not called <hi>imprecations,</hi> but <hi>atteſtations:</hi> And by the Statute-Law, an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> made 28 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.7. in theſe words, it is ſaid, <hi>No man, of what eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e degree, or condition ſoever he be, hath power to diſpence with Gods Law, as all the Clergy of this Realm in the ſaid Convocation, and moſt part of all the Univerſiteis of Chriſtendome; and we alſo do affirm and think, &amp;c.</hi> which makes void all Lawes, and practiſes, and cuſtomes, that are contrary to Chriſts Law, and the Apoſtles Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, which ſayes <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and <hi>above all things, my Brethren, ſwear not, neither by heaven nor earth, nor any other Oath, &amp;c.</hi> And to conclude this head, a lively Embleme we have this day practiſed in <hi>England,</hi> where it is practiſed, that thoſe who are called Noble-men of <hi>England,</hi> are not put to their oaths (as it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101371:11"/>is ſaid) in any caſe, but onely their teſtimony is taken upon their words, affirming or denying upon their Honours: And is there nothing left among Chriſtians in theſe our dayes, or the people of the Lord, that is as dear unto them, as an earthly great mans repute, and honour in the world is unto him? Bluſh for ſhame; and let it not be told in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publiſhed in <hi>Askelon,</hi> that Chriſtianity is grown out of repute, or that a true Chriſtian may not be believed when he ſpeaks in the preſence and fear of the Lord, although at the ſame time, and in the ſame caſe, he ſhall be believed, that teſtifies onely upon his earthly honour. And to this Courts Martial may not be an unfit preſident, who proceeds both to the tryal and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of perſons without an Oath, (taken by thoſe that ſit as Judges) and that upon this ground alſo, becauſe a Souldier is ſuppoſed to be ſo tender of his honour, that he will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach it by injuring another, or advantaging himſelf. So let all theſe things be put together, and what can be more clear, <hi>then that Oaths, or ſwearing men ſince the comming of Chriſt</hi> (before either they can be capable of office, or ſerving their Countrey, or their teſtimony be received in caſes of difference before Courts of Judicature) <hi>is a Popiſh Inſtitution,</hi> and hath no foundation or footing in the Scripture of truth, nor in the practiſe of the Primitive Chriſtians; nor hath not been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a teſtimony againſt it, by ſome in all ages, even down to this day?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Now follows the ſeverall inconveniences, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsarily follow the impoſition of Oaths which might be prevented, if ſwearing were not compelled.</head>
            <p>BEſides all that hath been ſaid, do not theſe inconveniences and miſchiefs neceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ily follow the impoſition of Oaths, or determining things by ſwearing? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not that which is called an Oath, (in many caſes) once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101371:11"/>untraverſable? As for inſtance, one man having ſworn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another poſitively, is not he that is ſworn againſt left without remedy? and do not thoſe before whom the oath is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (in ſome caſes) take themſelves concluded, and bound up by that oath, without any further examining witneſſes on the other ſide? or at leaſt if witneſſes be examined, of what force is their teſtimony, one or two men having ſworn poſitively the contrary? where often time the innocent are puniſhed, and the guilty go free, and the Author of evil undiſcovered: May it not be queried, Whether the Judge before whom the oath is taken, as aforeſaid, be clear of the blood of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, in this caſe, although or becauſe a Law made in the will of man requires it, contrary to the Law of Chriſt? if he or they be clear, was not Queen <hi>Mary</hi> as clear of the blood of the Martyrs, upon the ſame account, ſhe being a lawfull Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in that ſence? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, is it not unequal and unjuſt, that all men (in ſome caſes) ſhould be puniſhable for ſwearing, (though ignorantly and unawares and yet no man (in other caſes) to be puniſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at all, though they ſwear againſt their own knowledge, and that wilfully to, and this to be ordinary and common, as in the anſwers to the Bills in <hi>Chancery</hi> and <hi>Chequer?</hi> Which Bills will not be received without an oath; and they that dare not ſwear in obedience to Chriſts Command, hath been, and are impriſoned for contempt: ſo that he which departs from evil, makes himſelf a prey, and the keeping of Chriſts Commands are become a contempt: Do not theſe things make the times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lous? (let the upright judge) when on the contrary, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at ſwea s to his anſwer, though never ſo falſe, and againſt hs knowledge, and that to his own benefit (ſometimes) and pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udice of another, yet theſe men go unpuniſhed for their e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il, becauſe they care not what they ſwear; and the other is puniſhed by impriſonment, becauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fear an oath, and yet dare not but ſpeak the truth in their anſwers: So one man is puniſhed becauſe he cannot ſwear at all, (though his anſwer be true) and another man goes free, (though his anſwer be ſafe) becauſe he ſwears (although it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) to a lye, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſt his own knowledge, as many who are now in priſon for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101371:12"/>contempt, (ſo called) which contempt is only becauſe they cannot ſwear at all: So that in ſhort, one man is puniſhed when his anſwer is true, only becauſe he dare not ſwear, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man eſcapeth whenas his anſwer is falſe, becauſe he dare ſwear to a lye, (and the other dare not ſwear at all) as many priſons, Bills and Anſwers in <hi>Chancery</hi> and <hi>Chequor,</hi> may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Again, if a man ſwear to an Indictment, though never ſo falſe, yet it is commonly found upon that oath, when as the man ſworn againſt, knows not of it; yet that man, which (it may be) both maliciouſly and knowingly ſwears againſt his neighbour to his hurt, (it is ſaid) is not liable to be puniſhed by the Statute of Perjury, which miſchief might be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Witneſſes without ſwearing. Further, is not the way of determining of things by oath, not only injurious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal, but alſo attended with great and neceſſary inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies and evils, both to thoſe that command ſwearing, and to thoſe that do ſwear, as to thoſe that cannot ſwear at all for conſcience ſake?</p>
            <p>To thoſe that command ſwearing, who do not only break Chriſts Commands themſelves, but commands others ſo to do; but alſo are they not guilty of the forſwearing of others, whenas they command men to take ſuch oaths, as (before they give them) they themſelves know it is impoſſible to keep and obſerve, and yet do compel the taking of them, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the neglect? as in the oaths of Offices and Officers, as <hi>Sheriffs, Bayliffs, Conſtables,</hi> and others, beſides the oath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Freemen of Cities and Corporations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes and imployments, before entrance upon them, oaths are required to be taken, when in deed and in truth, bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe that give them, and thoſe that take them, knows that little or nothing is intended to be done or looked after, moe then the title of honor, and profit, and gain, that comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y them; though they ſwear to diſcharge their truſt, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch and ſuch things, which he that ſwears many times knows not what belongs to them, neither intends to trouble himſelf about them; as in ſeveral Offices relating to the Law, and Courts of Juſtice, and other places in the Common-wealth: Again, is not ſwearing made uſe of as a ſeal to hypocri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101371:12"/>both to him that commands it, and to him that obeys? Becauſe he that commands it, would not do it, but in order to his end, and the other would not take it, but for fear of a penalty, and becauſe he cannot avoid it, he takes it, but in his own ſenſe, and to his own end, and it may be quite contrary to the end of him that commanded it, or obtained to have it impoſed, and ſo both of them are deceived, and deciving one another: Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents for this, our dayes, as well as times paſt, may afford not a few; witneſs the ſeveral Oaths occaſioned by the ſeveral changes of late.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The inconveniences and miſchief that follow them that do ſwear: As fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, many people that do ſwear they underſtand not what an Ooth is, neither of that which is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Oath, many times they hear not one word that he which ſwears them, ſayes unto them, he ſpeaks them over ſo faſt; and the man knows nothing ſometimes until a book be put to his lips, and yet what this poor ignorant man, (having kiſſed the book) ſhall ſay, ſhall be of more force then divers witneſſes, that have not yet ſworn, or kiſſed the book; and it may be that he being on the affirmative, ſhall be more then two or three on the negative, who have better underſtood their Oaths, and ſpoken more to the purpoſe upon their oaths (as it is called) and ſo he that is ſworne on the affirmative, having once ſpoken a word, or ſworn to it, he dares not go back becauſe of his Oath; though upon hearing other witneſſes ſpeak to the ſame thing he may be better informed, but dare not own any infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, becauſe ſworn already to a contrary thing; which incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience would not be, if every man might witneſs forth his own knowledge without ſwearing, and yet to be puniſhed for a falſe teſtimony, as much as if he had ſworn falſe. Do not many mourn, and go heavily, becauſe of oaths in this and other caſes of the like nature?</p>
            <p>Again, Do not much hurt and miſchief come to many Swearers, becauſe they know the force of an Oath (taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Juſtice of Peace, or other Magiſtrate) to binde a man to the good Behaviour, or to the Peace, or to do him ſome other diſpleaſure, when indeed it is onely revenge and malice, though he takes his Oath (that ſpeaks) that it is for neither; and it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101371:13"/>may be that he that is ſworn againſt, will be as ready to ſwear againſt the Complainant, and that upon the ſame ground? Now doth not this gratifie the luſt and wickedneſs in people, and ſo much the more, becauſe a ſingle Oath will accompliſh his wicked end of evenge, without any other reſtimony, which would not be gratined, if ſo be that witneſſes were to prove the thing, or that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an deliver his knowledge of ſuch things without an Oath; otherwiſe how can the Magiſtrate be clear from guilt, not onely of the Planti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s ſwearing, but alſo of his ſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing maliciouſly and falſly? And alſo the ſame temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is in an Indictment, which one Party waiting to do his neighbour a miſchief may ſwear to, and the Indictment upon that Oath muſt be found, and that in the abſence of him that is indicted, as before hath been ſaid; and this Indictment (ſworn to by a malicious man) ſhall be the foundation to take away his life, if the Crime be of that nature: So that here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is another miſchief, whereby the luſts of wicked men are gratified with other caſes of the like nature, which might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The inconveniences that follows thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſwear at all for conſcience ſake, whereby many are made uncapable of being made Free of Cities and Corportations, and others are made un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apable of being ſerviceable in the Common-wealth, in any place or office of truſt; and others alſo are made unſerviceable as to give their teſtimony and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in caſes of difference between man and man; beſides many, who in divers caſes loſes the benefit of the Law of the Nation, becauſe that they cannot ſwear, and ſo by that means ſuffer the ſpoiling of their goods, and ungodly men make a prey upon them, knowing they cannot ſwear at all; which thing might be prevented, if according to the righteous Law of God, all things were eſtabliſhed out of the mouth of two or three Witneſſes, and thoſe that bore falſe witneſs, to be puniſhed as he ſhould have been againſt whom they have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, if their teſtimony had been true) which Law is equal and juſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This NATION which now mourns be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Oaths, might be preſerved from the Wrath and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101371:13"/>of God that hangs over this Nation, not onely becauſe of thoſe that command men to ſwear contrary to Chriſts Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; (and that, for to eſtabliſh cruelty and injuſtice) but alſo becauſe of thoſe that ſwear falſly, and that againſt their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for their own profit, and diſadvantage of others, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their wicked, malicious, and revengeful deſigns againſt the innocent, who dare not ſwear at all, and thereby are made a prey to the teeths of the Wolves, and to the wills of corrupt men, who take occaſion (as it were) <hi>to plough furrows upon the back of the poor, and to oppreſs the needy, for which thing ſake, the Wrath of God ſhall be poured out upon the head of the wicked, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall be on heaps, and the wiſe men ſhall be turned backward, and their table ſhall be a ſnare, and the curſe ſhall be upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, and they ſhall fall, and be broken, and riſe no more:</hi> And this may juſtly befall this Nation, becauſe of Oaths, and becauſe of oppreſſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Now follows a word of Advice to all thoſe who ſay the Scripture is their rule, and are zealous for the things contained therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOw all you that are ſeeking the Kingdom of Heaven in outward obſervations, (by which it comes not) and are taking up practiſes, by imitation from Commands laid down in the letter: Let me demand of you, Do you not finde this Command to proceed out of the mouth of Chriſt, <hi>viz. But I ſay unto you, ſwear not at all?</hi> And do not you finde the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>James</hi> abiding in this Doctrine? and hath it no room in your hearts? hath the traditions of your Fathers made it void to you? o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is it becauſe it cannot be practiſed without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, Fines and Impriſonment, and ſo will coſt you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which you cannot tell how to undergo, or part with, (you having not received the gift to ſuffer for his Names ſake?) or is your ſpirit different from <hi>Davids, (who would not offer an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to the Lord his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od of that which coſt him nothing?) in</hi> the fear of the Lord God of heaven and earth, (I beſeech you)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101371:14"/>conſider, is there not a Vail over your hearts untaken away to this day, that you cannot ſee nor underſtand this to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſts, with divers others, as plainly and as fully laid down in the letter, as thoſe you contend ſo much for? And may you not be as juſtly numbred amongſt thoſe that make their boaſt of the Law, and yet through breaking of the Law diſhonour God? Do ye think that the Lord will not ariſe to Judgement, and make you know that he is the Lord, and that you have not walked in his Statutes, neither executed his Judgements, but have done after the manner of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that are round about, (whoſe wayes <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not to learn, for their Cuſtomes were vain) <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 10.23. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 11.12. And upon a true and thorough ſearch, (when the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhall be ſearched out) will you not be found walking in the way of the Heathen, (ſpeaking their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean words, contrary to the language of the Scripture) and following their cuſtomes, (which are vain) in reſpecting of mens perſons which the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſayes, (<hi>James</hi> 2.9, 10.) whoever do, commits ſin, and are convinced of the Law as tranſgreſſors; <hi>For whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, is guilty of all.</hi> Mark that, and think not to cover your ſelves with ſaying it is meant of perſons in Judgement, for here is not a word ſpoken of Magiſtrates, but the words are general, and concerns all that regards Gods Law, as appears by the next words, <hi>viz. For whoſoever ſhall keep the whole, and yet offend in one point, &amp;c.</hi> And are not they out of the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who reſpecte perſons? who ſayes, <hi>How can ye believe, while ye receive honour one of another, and ſeeks not the honour that comes from God onely. (John</hi> 5.44. <hi>Matthew</hi> 22.16.) <hi>God onely.</hi> Mark, <hi>from God onely;</hi> and he himſelf practiſed this Doctrine for he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther received honour from man, nor regarded any mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as his very enemies bore teſtimony of him, that he taught the way of God truly, and regarded no mans perſon. But is not this Command alſo too dear for you? Will it not coſt you too much to practiſe? Do you not know it will hinder your promotion in the world? Are you not more afraid (that if you ſhould refuſe to reſpect mens perſons, and to give ſlattering
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101371:14"/>titles to men, (<hi>Job.</hi> 32.21, 22.) the Goaler would take you away, then that your Maker would ſoon take you away, if you did do it; and is not this a Command, that you ſhould not be conformed to this world? <hi>Romans</hi> 12.2.16. and that you ſhould not conform to men of high degree, but condiſcend to men of low degree? are not theſe, with others, the Commands of Chriſt? and are not you too much like the profeſſing <hi>Jews</hi> herein, who had plentifull knowledge of the letter without them, but had not his word abiding in them? Though they could diſpute and reaſon with Chriſt, and againſt his Apoſtles, with the word of truth, yet Chriſt tells them plainly, his Word was not abiding in them, which the Saints had received from Chriſt, whereby they were made clean, and by it (which dwells richly in them) they made melody in their hearts to God; and <hi>David</hi> the Servant of the Lord, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.6.11. by the word which he had in his heart, he was kept from ſin againſt God, and thereby had reſpect to all Gods Commands. Now examine your ſelves, and try your own ſelves, whether you be in the Faith, and the ſame Word of Life be in you, and whoſe ſteps you walk in, and whom you are found imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of; whether <hi>Abraham,</hi> who forſook his Country to go to the Land which the Lord had ſhewed him? and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſteps, who choſe rather to ſuffer with the people of God, then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the pleaſure of ſin for a ſeaſon? or whether you do not walk in the ſteps of him whom you ſo often upbraid others with, namely <hi>Naaman,</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> who ſpoke good words, and yet could not forſake his old Maſter, to ſerve the Lord fully, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.18. But when he went into the houſe of <hi>Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> his Maſter leaning on his hand, and he bowed down him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>in that thing he would be pardoned.</hi> Mark, <hi>In this thing pardon thy Servant;</hi> he knew it was evil, and deſired pardon for it; and yet when his Maſter leaned upon his hand, he muſt bow, leaſt he ſhould loſe his place, and gain his Maſters diſpleaſure. Now examine your ſelves, doth not ſomething let you ſee, (that notwithſtanding all the Lord hath done for you, and all that you have ever taſted or enjoyed from him) yet there is this thing, or the other thing, that you continue in the practiſe of, for one end o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other, which you know you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101371:15"/>ſhould not do; and in words you deſire pardon for them, but you ſtill continue in the ſame practiſe, your very prayers wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing againſt you; and like thoſe, <hi>James</hi> 4.3. you are <hi>ſtill ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but receive not, becauſs you ask amiſs, to ſpend it upon your Luſts;</hi> ſtill to continue in your Maſters ſervice, in conforming to the cuſtomes and faſhions of the world, and in walking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the traditions of your Fathers, as in particular in this caſe of ſwearing, which Chriſt hath ſo plainly and ſully forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and therefore your prayers return as dung in your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, your conſciences condemning of you, the which if you did regard to keep void of offence, both towards God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men, (in the light of Chriſt) you would have confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence towards God, and <hi>whatſoever you asked of him, you would receive, becauſe you keep his Commandements, and do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight, John</hi> 3.22. But now is blindneſs, barrenneſs, and leanneſs of ſoul upon you, and yet you cry you are rich, and you ſee, and have need of nothing, and hateth and diſputeth againſt that which letteth you ſee the things which have need of pardon, and ſo you are <hi>loaden with Sin, and led away with divers Luſts, alwayes learning, never able to come to the knowledge of the truth;</hi> and therefore are not free, and in your principles conclude never can be, while you are in this world; and ſo by what hath been ſaid, you may ſee, (your own condition as a man ſees his face in a Glaſs) how that you not only reſpect mens perſons, preferring one before another, but alſo Chriſts Commands, picking out what you like, and what may keep you in the repute of the world, and preſerve you in the preferment thereof, but thoſe that may expoſe you to hazzard, or make you liable to the worlds ſcorn, though as fully and expreſly required by Chriſt (of all his followe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s) to be kept and obſerved, you let ſlip, and paſs by, as a thing of nought: But <hi>be not deceived, God will not be mocked, for what a man ſoweth, that ſhall he reap; he that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap Corruption:</hi> And this ſhall you aſſure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receive at his hand, (if you repent not of your double min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>you ſhall lye down in ſorrow, and he ſhall laugh at your Calamity, and mock when your fear comes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101371:15"/>
            <head>Now follows ſome reaſons or grounds, whereby the Spiritual eye, or the man whoſe underſtanding is opened, may come to ſee the neceſsity of the ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſwearing, ſince the dayes of Christs coming in the fleſh.</head>
            <p>FIrſt, Becauſe all the things of the Law were but ſhadows of the good things to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. <hi>But Chriſt is the ſubſtance of all thoſe types and ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ows, and is come into the world, and is manifeſt in his Saints, and true Chriſtians, and hath given them an underſtanding whereby they know him that is true, and are in him that is true, and he in them, and he works all their works for them, and in them,</hi> and teacheth them to ſpeak truth ſimply, without guile or fraud, <hi>and as he is, ſo are they in this world,</hi> and believes in him, and follows his ſteps, who is the truth, and in whoſe mouth there was found no guile.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe ſwearing implyes unbelief, to be either in the perſon ſwearing, or in him for whoſe ſake the oath is taken or ſworn; which is not to be ſuppoſed to be in thoſe (as predominant or ruling) who are Saints, or true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who are redeemed not only from a vile, but a vain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation alſo, and from the traditions of their Fathers, (that are not after Chriſt) and from fear and unbelief alſo, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very evil word and way, and are called unto holineſs and truth, and are without fault before the Throne of God, which things are found in the new heart, that is Gods gift, and in the new man that is created after God, and renewed in knowledge after the Image of him that created him, and ſo they are come to the end of all oaths, and out of fears, and doubts, and unbelief, to have ſtrong conſolation through Chriſt Jeſus, the way to the Father.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe herein; namely, by the aboliſhing of ſwearing, do the excellency, precedency, and eminency of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101371:16"/>New Covenant, exceed the Old; for the Old in this was faulty, <hi>viz.</hi> that it made nothing perfect, but this New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and better hope doth; for in this Covenant all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Lord are taught of the Lord, and great is their peace, and out of ſtrife and contention, and the uſe of Oaths are they come; into the Covenant of Light and Peace, in which they reſt with God, in the ſenſe of the forgiveneſs of their fins, and the bleſſedneſs of their ſtate, wherein their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is remembred no more; for <hi>their Tents are beautifull, and their habitations are pleaſant:</hi> And here is <hi>Jacob</hi> inheriting the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>in whom God ſees no ſin;</hi> and the true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, who walks according to the rule, and <hi>in whom he ſees no iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but peace is his portion for ever. Of what hath been ſpoken, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the ſum, that Chriſt hath forbid all manner of ſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng in all caſes whatſoever; and this Doctrine was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Apoſtles, and practiſed by the true Chriſtians in the firſt ages of the Church, and hath been ſealed with the blood of Martyrs, and borne witneſs to by ſome in all ages, down to this day, and the contrary practiſe is a <hi>Popiſh Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and a <hi>Jeſuiticall</hi> deſign to keep down the true headſhip of the Church, and to ſet up him, and to keep his Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m the Lord is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſing to deſtroy with the Spirit of his mouth, (and to conſume with the brightneſs of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) who hath been, and is the cauſe of ſo much bloodſhed, and diſcord, and variance, among the Children of men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Self hath kept the Thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and Equity and Righteouſneſs hath fallen in the ſtreets, and he that departs from iniquity, hath made himſelf a prey, and the manner and cuſtomes of the Heathen hath been followed, even by thoſe who have profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a zeal for Chriſt and his Commands, who while they have been profeſſing of them, have made them void by the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, and true Chriſtianity with Saintſhip, (by their means) is become a reproach, and the Name of the Lord hath been Blaſphemed among the Heathen, becauſe of theſe things; but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord is ariſing, <hi>(as a Giant refreſhed with Wine)</hi> who hath ſeen the deſolate ſtate of his Spouſe, and is ſaying to <hi>Son, Ariſe ſhine thy light is come, for the Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the Lord is riſen upon thee, ſhake off the duſt from thy feet, put on thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101371:16"/>garment for thou ſhalt be no more termed deſolute, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, and to the brightneſs of thy riſing ſhall Nations come, and Princes to thy beauty, and the glory and the riches of the Nations ſhall be laid down at thy feet, and thou ſhalt be crowned with renown for ever, and the everlaſting gates ſhall be opened, and the righteous Nation that keeps the truth, ſhall enter in; and none ſhall be able to make them afraid, (but the ſwearers and lyars ſhall be ſhut out)</hi> and this is the Heritage of the Servants of the Lord foreve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>But <hi>becauſe of ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and whoring, they break out, and blood toucheth blood, therefore ſhall the Land mourn, and every one that dwells therein ſhall be cut off,</hi> Hoſea 4.2.3.</p>
            <p>From henceforth let no man think it ſtrange, that any denies to ſwear <hi>at all,</hi> but rather wonder, that the God of this world ſhould ſo long have blinded the mindes of them that believe not, (in the light of the Son of God) leaſt by the ſhining of the light in their hearts, they ſhould come to the knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Chriſt, and by him ſhould be taught to ſpeak truth without ſwearing, and ſo he become the Head over all things to the Church, who is God over all, bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
